Guide to the Margaret Fishback Papers, 1863-1978 and undated RL.00397
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Writings Series, 1926-1978 and undated, 17 boxes
  - Poetry Subseries, 1926-1978 and undated
    - Compilations, 1931-1968 and undated
      - One to a Customer, 1937-1938 and undated
        - Indices, undated (Box 16)
        - Publicity, 1937-1938 and undated (Box 16)
      - Out of My Head, 1933 and undated
        - Draft and tentative table of contents, undated (Box 16)
        - Publicity and reviews, photograph portrait, 1933 and undated (Box 16)
      - Poems Made Up to Take Out, 1943-1963 and undated
        - Book and catalog card, 1963 and undated (Box 16)
        - Book preparation: indices, poems, notes, 1961-1962 (Box 16)
        - Book preparation: published materials, 1943-1962, 2 folders (Box 17)
        - Clippings re: McKay book, undated (Box 17)
        - Correspondence, 1962-1963, 2 folders (Box 17)
        - Drafts and notes, 1962-1963 and undated (Box 17)
        - Poems, Not in McKay book, 1946-1963 (Items removed to Oversize Materials, box OV2) (Box 17)
        - [Proof and illustrations, undated, removed to Oversize Materials, box OV4] (Box 17)
        - Publicity and reviews, 1963 (Box 17)
        - Publicity photographs and caricature, 1963 and undated (Box 17)
        - Typed manuscript of book before McKay selections, undated (Box 17)
      - Signs of Life: Draft, 1931 (Box 17)
      - Time for a Quick One, 1940
        - Autographed book, 1940 (Box 17)
        - Contract, 1940 (Box 17)
        - Publicity and reviews, 1940 (Box 17)
    - Individual Poems, 1926-1978 and undated
      Includes poems, published and unpublished, that appeared individually in magazines and newspapers. Also includes a list, compiled by Fishback, of her published poems from 1926-1930.
      Several published versions of these poems were compiled by Fishback into scrapbooks and can be found in the Scrapbooks Subseries.
      - Drafts, 1926-1974 and undated
        Folders titled Assorted drafts contain drafts of Fishback's individual poems, titled and untitled, arranged chronologically. Otherwise, original folder titles have been retained and are arranged alphabetically by folder title.
        - Astronauts, with notes and clippings, 1968 (Box 18)
        - Bird rhymes and letters, 1961 and undated (Box 18)
        - Cape Cod Compass project, 1964-1965 (1 item removed to Oversize Materials, box OV3) (Box 18)
        - Christmas Verse--ideas, 1947-1952 and undated (Box 18)
        - [ Dream Men of Fair Women collection galley proof, Stage, 1936, removed to Oversize Materials, box OV2] (Box 18)
        - From Zero to Hero, 1954 (Box 18)
        - Growing Pains, 1963 (Box 18)
        - Kid Stuff (as tho by kids), 1949 and undated (Box 18)
        - New York, 1961-1963 and undated (Box 18)
          Includes poems, notes, clippings, pamphlets, and correspondence with Gurney Williams.
        - Personal, 1935-1972 and undated (Box 18)
          Includes poems written for anniversaries, birthdays, holiday greetings, and other events; some poems were written for people to give to other people.
        - Rhymes to revise and re-route, 1932-1953 and undated (Box 18)
        - Seasonal Verse--ideas, 1950-1952 and undated (Box 18)
        - Assorted drafts, 1926-1974 and undated
          - 1926-1942, 5 folders (Box 18)
          - 1943-1966, 12 folders (Box 19)
          - 1967-1974 and undated, 5 folders (Box 20)
      - Published Works, 1926-1978 and undated
        Folders titled Assorted contain clippings of Fishback's individual published poems, arranged chronologically. Other folders contain the publications in which the poems originally appeared, arranged alphabetically by title.
        - Be it ever so humble, there is nothing like fresh air, Woman's Day, 1962 (Box 20)
        - The complacent cliff-dweller, Here's to Your New Home...Cheers!, 1978 (Box 20)
        - Doggerel for diplomats, Time, 1968 (Box 20)
        - Double-crostic puzzle solutions, Saturday Review, 1964 (Box 20)
        - Hallowe'en, Woman's Day, 1961 (Box 20)
        - How not to be invited again, Ingenue, 1960 (Box 20)
        - [Illustrations for unnamed Woman's Day spread, circa 1962, removed to Oversize Materials, box OV1] (Box 20)
        - [King Features Syndicate proofs for Sunday Pictorial Review covers, 1952, removed to Oversize Materials, box OV2] (Box 20)
        - Look on the Light Side, 1957 (Box 20)
        - Old Farmer's Almanac and related materials, 1966-1967 (Box 20)
        - [ Saturday Evening Post tear sheets, 1939-1940, including Slaughter Down East and Claustrophobia on the Home Grounds, removed to Oversize Materials, box OV2] (Box 20)
        - Sauce Unlimited and related materials, 1963-1964 (Box 21)
        - [ A Song for Christmas Shoppers, Today's Woman, undated, removed to Oversize Materials, box OV1] (Box 21)
        - [ Stalin's Happiest Subjects, This Week Magazine, 1949, removed to Oversize Materials, box OV2] (Box 21)
        - [ Things my Mother Never Told Me, New York Times supplement, A Better World through Electronics (advertisement), 1962, removed to Oversize Materials, box OV2] (Box 21)
        - Those touchy teens, Woman's Day, 1960 (Box 21)
        - [ Underprivileged, Look, 1966, removed to Oversize Materials, box OV2] (Box 21)
        - Untitled poem printed on miniature rolling pin, undated (Box 21)
        - Warning! May Be Habit Forming, 1961 (Box 41)
        - Will you be my valentine?, Woman's Day, 1962 (Box 21)
        - Assorted, 1926-1969, 8 folders; items removed to Oversize Materials, box OV2 (Box 21)
        - Assorted, undated (Box 22)
      - List of published poems from 1926-1930, undated (Box 22)
  - Prose Subseries, 1928-1970 and undated
    The materials in this subseries document Fishback's prose work, including published and unpublished articles, book projects, a column called Woman-Talk, and some works of short fiction. Preparatory materials such as drafts, clippings, and handwritten notes provide contextual information for some of the published items. Book projects additionally feature publicity materials and reviews.
    Several published versions of works in this subseries were compiled by Fishback into scrapbooks and can be found in the Scrapbooks Subseries.
    - Articles, 1928-1965 and undated
      Materials include published articles, drafts, and preparatory materials such as news clippings and handwritten notes.
      - Drafts, 1928-1965 and undated
        - Debutante article, 1937 and undated (Box 22)
          Includes draft, notes, and clippings.
        - Hostess article, 1930 (Box 22)
          Includes draft, notes on the draft, and the published article.
        - Lesley Frost article, 1962-1965 (Box 22)
          This article about Lesley Frost, children's author and daughter of Robert Frost, was commissioned by Yankee magazine in 1963. Materials include a draft of the article, as well as correspondence regarding its inception, notes, clippings, and several Robert Frost obituaries.
        - Assorted drafts, 1928-1965 and undated, 5 folders (Box 22)
          Materials include drafts of individual articles, titled and untitled, arranged chronologically.
      - Published works, 1927-1959 and undated, 4 folders; items removed to Oversize Materials, boxes OV1-OV3 (Box 22)
    - Books, 1935-1969 and undated
      Materials include published prose works and an unpublished book project, with accompanying preparatory materials such as drafts, manuscripts, notes, and clippings, as well as publicity materials and reviews.
      Arranged alphabetically by book title.
      - A Child's Book of Natural History, 1935-1969 (Box 23)
        - Clippings, 1935-1969 (Box 23)
        - Correspondence and contract, 1968-1969 (Box 23)
        - Drafts and notes, 1968-1969, 2 folders (Box 23)
        - Publicity, 1969 (Box 23)
      - First Book of Manners: Notes and clippings, 1963-1964 and undated (Box 23)
      - Look Who's a Mother!, 1942-1945
        - Book and pamphlet, 1945 (Box 23)
        - Contract, 1942 (Box 23)
      - Safe Conduct: When to Behave--And Why, 1938-1958
        - Correspondence, 1938-1958 (Box 23)
        - Drafts of chapters, undated (Box 23)
        - Drafts of poems, list of alternate titles, and other materials, 1938 and undated (Box 23)
        - First draft, undated (Box 23)
        - [Illustrations, undated, removed to Oversize Materials, box OV1] (Box 23)
        - Manuscript, undated, 2 folders (Box 23)
        - [Proof, 1938, removed to Oversize Materials, box OV3] (Box 23)
        - Radio script, For Men Only show, 1939 (Box 24)
        - Reprints in magazines, 1938 and undated (Box 24)
        - Reviews and publicity, 1938-1939 (Box 24)
      - Untitled Scotland book collaboration with Graham Hunter, 1967-1969, 3 folders (Box 24)
        This book collaboration was designed as a follow-up to a book written by Hunter's late wife, Pat Bowman, entitled The Scot and Finella. The materials include correspondence, a composition book, handwritten notes, clippings, financial materials, and a photograph of Bowman.
    - Column, Woman-Talk, 1943-1947 and undated
      The Woman-Talk column appeared in Liberty magazine from 1943-1947. Materials here include clippings of the published column as well as preparatory materials, including drafts, clippings, and handwritten notes.
      - Drafts and clippings, 1943-1945, 6 folders (Box 24)
      - Drafts and clippings, 1946 (Box 25)
      - Old Liberty materials, 1945-1947 and undated (Box 25)
      - Published materials, 1943-1947, 2 folders (Box 25)
    - Fiction, 1928-1970 and undated
      - Business Before Pleasure, 1933 (Box 25)
      - French cat story to accompany Eva Kane painting, 1970 (Box 25)
      - Old letters for store story, 1928 (Box 25)
      - Assorted short stories, 1932-1933 and undated (Box 25)
  - Scrapbooks Subseries, 1926-1962 and undated
    This subseries includes scrapbooks assembled by Fishback, some in preparation for poetry compilations. The scrapbooks contain chiefly clippings of published poetry, but also include unpublished drafts, correspondence, and other clippings. A scrapbook of Macy's advertisements is located in the Advertising Series.
    - Home copy: Current verse thru 1941 plus others eliminated in first selection, 1928-1940, 5 folders (Box 25)
      Includes clippings of Fishback's published works, chiefly poetry, as well as unpublished drafts with Fishback's notes regarding their sale. Also in this scrapbook is a set of notecards including titles of poems and their publication information. The eliminated materials referenced in the scrapbook's title refer to Time for a Quick One (1940).
    - Poetry scrapbook, 1926-1938 and undated (Box 26)
    - Prose and poetry scrapbook, 1926-1939 (Box 26)
    - M.F.A. scrap book being worked on 1961-1962, 1952-1962, 5 folders (Box 26)
      Includes chiefly clippings of Fishback's published poetry, as well as correspondence with Kenneth Collins and clippings of his Women's Wear Daily column, Today and Yesterday in Retailing, in which Fishback's poetry was frequently mentioned. Also included in this scrapbook are published advertising copy, correspondence with publishers, a biographical article, and poetry by Fishback's son Tony. This scrapbook was apparently compiled in the preparation of Poems Made Up to Take Out (1963).
  - Speeches Subseries, 1936-1965
    The speeches in this subseries were prepared for a variety of events, including an advertising convention, a convention of the American Gas Association, a book and author luncheon, a school meeting, and other events.
    - The Customer Who's Never Right, 1964 (Box 26)
    - Institutional Advertising, 1939 (Box 26)
    - Script for Fearless Frank's speech to Ernie, undated (Box 26)
    - Whose Side Am I On? 1965 (Box 26)
    - Various speeches and related materials, 1936-1963 (Box 26)
  - Other Writings Subseries, 1933-1973 and undated
    This subseries contains a variety of miscellaneous Fishback writings, including writings in genres atypical of Fishback such as song lyrics and limericks. Also included are poems by Fishback's son Tony, on which Fishback occasionally collaborated.
    - Analysis of That Certain Flavor by Lee Rogow, 1949 (Box 26)
    - Blurbs, undated (Box 26)
    - Book notices, cover art, 1932-1940 (Box 39)
    - Etiquette materials, 1961, 1970, and undated (Box 26)
    - Happy birthday advertisement for P.G. Wodehouse, 1960 (Box 26)
    - Ideas: Notes and clippings, 1964 (Box 26)
    - Letters to the editor, 1933-1968 (Box 26)
    - Limericks for Journal-American, 1939 and undated (Box 27)
    - List of likes and dislikes, undated (Box 27)
    - Musical score, The Old Order Changeth for the Better, words by Marne, undated (Box 27)
    - Notebooks, 1938-1970 and undated, 6 folders (Box 27)
    - Notes, 1908, 1945-1970 and undated, 4 folders (Box 27)
    - Notes, 1968-1973 and undated (Box 28)
    - Poems (clippings), 1939-1961 (Box 39)
    - Silver Burdett Company, 1964, 2 folders (Box 28)
      Materials pertaining to the production of a series of elementary school textbooks containing folk songs from around the world. Materials include correspondence, musical scores, lyrics, drafts, notes, and financial and legal records.
    - Song lyrics, My Current Perplexity and Never Was a Baby, undated (Box 28)
    - Success in a Baked Potato and untitled, 1950 (Box 28)
    - WQXR Composer's Contest, 1973 (Box 28)
    - Writings with and by son Tony, 1948-1964 (Box 28)
- Advertising Series, 1926-1974 and undated, 10 boxes
  The Advertising Series documents Fishback's advertising work for R.H. Macy and Co., as well as work for advertising agencies and freelance work. Included in this series are advertisements in various stages of production: notes, drafts, proofs, and tear sheets. Administrative materials, such as correspondence, often accompany the advertisements. Also represented in this series is evidence of Fishback's professional affiliations, particularly with the Advertising Women of New York (AWNY). Materials generated or collected in the process of preparing for speaking engagements with professional societies are also included. The series also includes a small collection of trade literature, chiefly books on advertising topics written by other authors.
  The series is arranged into four subseries--Macy's, Client Files, Conferences and Professional Societies, and Other Advertising Files--and alphabetically therein.
  - Macy's Subseries, 1927-1970 and undated
    Materials in this subseries document Fishback's advertising work for R.H. Macy and Co. (Macy's), where she was employed as a copywriter from 1927-1942. Materials represent her work as a divisional copywriter as well as her institutional work. Institutional advertisements often contain the Macy's slogans It's smart to be thrifty and No one is in debt to Macy's. Advertisements and advertisement copy are included, as well as administrative files such as correspondence, company publications, and awards.
    Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
    - Advertisements, 1927-1967 and undated
      - [Scrapbook, 1929-1930, removed to Oversize Materials, box OV5] (Box 28)
      - Scrapbook, 1929-1930 (Use Copy) (Box 29)
      - Divisional Advertisements, 1927-1933 and undated
        - [Blankets, towels, bedspreads, 1931 and undated, removed to Oversize Materials, box OV6] (Box 29)
        - [Costume Jewelry Department, undated, removed to Oversize Materials, box OV7] (Box 29)
        - [Furniture, undated, removed to Oversize Materials, box OV6] (Box 29)
        - [Gloves, undated, removed to Oversize Materials, box OV7] (Box 29)
        - Good Foods/Groceries, 1932-1933 and undated (Items removed to Oversize Materials, box OV6) (Box 29)
        - [Housewares, undated, removed to Oversize Materials, box OV6] (Box 29)
        - Infants' and Children's Departments, 1930-1932 and undated (Items removed to Oversize Materials, box OV6) (Box 29)
        - [Lingerie Department, undated, removed to Oversize Materials, box OV6] (Box 29)
        - Luggage, 1927 and undated (Items removed to Oversize Materials, box OV6) (Box 29)
        - [Maids' uniforms, undated, removed to Oversize Materials, box OV6] (Box 29)
        - Mattress Department, undated (Box 29)
        - Men's Department, undated (Items removed to Oversize Materials, box OV6) (Box 29)
        - Needlecraft and Notions Departments, 1932 and undated (Items removed to Oversize Materials, box OV6) (Box 29)
        - Optical Department, undated (Box 29)
        - [Personal Shopping Service, undated, removed to Oversize Materials, box OV6] (Box 29)
        - [Place de l'opera, 1933, removed to Oversize Materials, box OV7] (Box 29)
        - Stockings, undated (Box 29)
        - Toys, undated (Box 29)
        - [Wine and Liquor Store, undated, removed to Oversize Materials, box OV6] (Box 29)
      - Institutional Advertisements (General), 1927-1967 and undated
        - Copy, 1939-1961 (Box 29)
        - Photostat proofs, 1928-1939 and undated, 2 folders; items removed to Oversize Materials, box OV7 (Box 29)
        - Portfolio, Tentative Institutional Copy for Fall 1941, 1941 (Box 29)
        - Proofs, 1927-1941 and undated (Items removed to Oversize Materials, boxes OV7-OV9) (Box 29)
        - [Sketches for illustrations, 1943 and undated, removed to Oversize Materials, box OV9] (Box 29)
        - [Sketches for illustrations, 1947 and undated, removed to Oversize Materials, box OV8] (Box 29)
        - Tear sheets, 1932-1948 (Items removed to Oversize Materials, box OV8) (Box 29)
        - Tear sheets, 1962-1967 (Box 29)
        - Who's Who in Toyland booklet, undated, removed to Oversize Materials, box OV9] (Box 29)
      - Institutional Advertisements (Topical), 1930-1967 and undated
        - Christmas, 1930-1964 and undated (Items removed to Oversize Materials, box OV8) (Box 29)
        - Diamonds, 1961-1967 (Items removed to Oversize Materials, box OV8) (Box 29)
        - Drugs and cosmetics, 1963 (Box 29)
        - [Macy's Barnyard, undated, removed to Oversize Materials, box OV8] (Box 29)
        - [Macy's Information Clerk, undated, removed to Oversize Materials, box OV8] (Box 29)
        - Six Appeal flipbook, undated (Box 29)
        - Thanksgiving Parade, 1942-1946 and undated (Items removed to Oversize Materials, box OV8) (Box 29)
    - Awards, 1937 and 1939 (Box 30-31)
      Two plaques, Annual Advertising Awards (1937) and Publishers Service Company Annual Award (1939)
    - Awards program, 1938 (Box 32)
    - Clippings, 1939 and 1972 (Box 32)
    - Correspondence, general, 1928-1966 and undated (1 item removed to Oversize Materials, box OV9) (Box 32)
    - Correspondence regarding W. Bingham's retirement, 1961 (Box 32)
    - Eldridge, Irving C., 1965 (Box 32)
      Obituary and photograph, Irving C. Eldridge, Display Director of Macy's New York.
    - Ephemera (ribbon), undated (Box 32)
    - Jack Strauss poem and David Yunich Christmas speech, 1961-1966, 2 folders; items removed to Oversize Materials, box OV9 (Box 32)
    - Notebook and loose notes, undated (Box 32)
    - Photograph, Margaret Fishback and others, undated (Box 32)
    - Portfolios, 1937-1938 (Box 40)
    - Posters, proofs, 1930-1938 (Box 41)
    - Print copy, 1924-1927; 2 folders (Box 39)
    - Print copy, 1929-1930s (Box 40)
    - Print copy--Newspaper, 1928-1930s, 1959-1964 (Box 41)
    - Printed materials, 1933-1966 and undated (Box 32)
      Company publications, including brochures and copies of internal newsletters The Macy Star and Macy News.
    - Rhymes on magnet bulletin board for Branky on his retirement from Macy's, 1950 (Box 32)
    - Scrapbook of advertising, 1928-1930 (Box 42)
    - Scrapbook of advertising, 1928-1939 (Box 43)
    - Scrapbook of advertising, 1928-1940 (Box 44)
    - [Sheet music, To Thee, O Macy's Proud and Strong, undated, removed to Oversize Materials, box OV9] (Box 32)
  - Client Files Subseries, 1931-1973 and undated
    Includes advertising proofs, advertising copy, tear sheets, correspondence, photographs, clippings, competitive advertisements, and other materials related to work Fishback completed for specific clients. Advertising work in this subseries was completed both freelance and while Fishback worked for advertising agencies.
    Arranged alphabetically by client name.
    - American Artists Group, 1957 (Box 32)
    - American Express, 1961 (Box 32)
    - Arrow, 1958-1959 (Items removed to Oversize Materials, box OV10) (Box 32)
    - [Ballantine Beer, undated, removed to Oversize Materials, box OV11] (Box 32)
    - Banana-O, 1961 (Box 41)
    - Barton's Candy Corporation, 1960-1964 and undated (1 item removed to Oversize Materials, box OV11) (Box 32)
    - Barton's Candy Corporation, approximately 1960 (Box 39)
    - Barton's Candy Corporation--Christmas, Easter, Passover, 1960-1961 (Box 41)
    - Barton's Candy Corporation--Passover Seder poster, approximately 1960 (Box 41)
    - Better Vision Institute, 1948-1955 (1 item removed to Oversize Materials, box OV11) (Box 32)
    - Bliss Fiberglas, 1963-1964 (Box 32)
    - Borden's, 1958-1959 (Items removed to Oversize Materials, box OV11) (Box 32)
    - Brokaw Brothers, 1930s (Box 39)
    - Brooklyn Museum Industrial Design Division, undated (1 item removed to Oversize Materials, box OV11) (Box 33)
    - Burlington Industries, 1955 (Box 33)
    - Burma-Shave, 1965 (Box 33)
    - Chef Boy-Ar-Dee, 1959 (Items removed to Oversize Materials, box OV11) (Box 33)
    - Clairol, 1964-1965, 2 folders; items removed to Oversize Materials, box OV11 (Box 33)
    - Dennison, 1941-1950 (Box 33)
    - DeSoto cars, 1940 (Items removed to Oversize Materials, box OV12) (Box 33)
    - Dorothy Gray, Your Dowry of Beauty, 1930 (Box 33)
    - DuPont, 1948-1958 (Box 33)
    - DuPont Rug Anchors, approximately 1960 (Box 39)
    - Flexalum, approximately 1960 (Box 39)
    - Flexalum, 1960-1961 (Box 41)
    - Fortnum & Mason's, 1929 (Box 39)
    - General Foods Gourmet Foods, 1959 (Box 39)
    - General Foods Kitchens, 1959 (Box 33)
    - Gimbels, 1969 and undated (Items removed to Oversize Materials, box OV10) (Box 33)
    - Gourmet Foods, 1959 (Box 33)
    - Great Atlantic & Pacific Tea Company (A&P), 1931-1959 and undated (Items removed to Oversize Materials, box OV10) (Box 33)
    - Great Atlantic & Pacific Tea Company (A&P), 1930s (Box 40)
    - Hanes hosiery, 1955 and undated (Box 34)
    - Hoffman Beverage Company, 1951 (Box 34)
    - Kellogg's, 1941 (Items removed to Oversize Materials, box OV10) (Box 34)
    - Loft's Candy, 1957 (Items removed to Oversize Materials, box OV4) (Box 34)
    - Martex ( The Magic Towel), 1961-1963, 2 folders; items removed to Oversize Materials, box OV10 (Box 34)
    - Martex (The Magic Towel), 1960s (Box 39)
    - Moore-McCormack (Mooremack) Cruise Lines, 1959 (Box 39)
    - Max Schling, Jr. (florist), 1964 (Box 34)
    - McCord Radiator and Manufacturing Company, 1933 (Box 34)
    - Moore-McCormack (Mooremack) Cruise Lines, 1958-1959, 3 folders (Box 34)
    - National Safety Council, 1947 and undated (Items removed to Oversize Materials, box OV12) (Box 34)
    - Nazareth, 1949-1950 (Items removed to Oversize Materials, box OV10) (Box 34)
    - [Nemo, undated, removed to Oversize Materials, box OV10] (Box 34)
    - NItey-Nite, 1960-1961 (Box 41)
    - Norcross, 1958-1960, 2 folders; items removed to Oversize Materials, box OV12 (Box 34)
    - Norcross, 1959 (Box 40)
    - Norsk, 1967-1968, 2 folders (Box 35)
    - Ohrbach's, 1958-1961 (Box 35)
    - Ohrbach's, 1960 (Box 39)
    - Pabst Blue Ribbon, 1951, 2 folders (Box 35)
    - Salada, 1962 (Box 39)
    - Sanforized, 1958 (Box 41)
    - Seagram's, 1951 (Box 35)
    - Simmons Beautyrest, 1959 (Items removed to Oversize Materials, box OV12) (Box 35)